<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the assizes in St. Maries Church in request of George Ashby Esq., High-Sheriff of the said county by Thomas Sawbridge, Vicar of Harstone, July the 25th, 1689.</title>
            <author>Sawbridge, Thomas, Vicar of Harstone.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62266</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S782</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37193</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12064207</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12064207</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53338</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62266)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53338)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 822:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the assizes in St. Maries Church in request of George Ashby Esq., High-Sheriff of the said county by Thomas Sawbridge, Vicar of Harstone, July the 25th, 1689.</title>
                  <author>Sawbridge, Thomas, Vicar of Harstone.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.B. for Francis Ward ... :</publisher>
                  <publisher>and are to be sold by R. Taylor in London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah I, 26 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53338:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53338:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at the Aſſizes in St. <hi>Maries</hi> Church in <hi>Leiceſter</hi> At the Requeſt of <hi>George Aſhby</hi> Eſq; High-Sheriff of the ſaid County.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Thomas Sawbridge</hi> Vicar of <hi>Harſtone, July</hi> the <hi>25th.</hi> 1689.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. B.</hi> for <hi>Francis Ward,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> and are to be Sold by <hi>R. Taylor</hi> in <hi>London.</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:53338:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53338:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached at the Aſſizes in St. <hi>Maries</hi> Church in <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the <hi>1.26.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And I will reſtore thy Judges as at the firſt, and thy Counſellors as at the beginning: afterwards thou ſhalt be called the City of Righteouſneſs, the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful City.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WHat was but here promiſed to the <hi>Jews,</hi> is, thanks to the Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and the Care of our Gracious King and Queen (as we hope) in a great meaſure granted to us of this Age and Nation, and of this Scripture may I uſe the words of our Saviour, concerning another Part of this Propheſy; <hi>this day is this Scripture fulfilled,</hi> and that not only in our Ears, but to our Eyes, we at this time beholding the happy Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of our Reformation, reſtoring to us our
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53338:3"/>juſt Laws and Liberties, even ſuch Judges as were at the firſt, as well as ſuch Counſellors as were at the beginning; and therefore have good ground to hope our City ſhall become Righteous and a Faithful City; that we ſhall be a Nation beloved of God, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected by him, and that in return thereto we act and live as thoſe who prize theſe Mercies, and live up to thoſe great ends for which God hath done ſuch great things for us already, whereof we rejoyce, and not the leaſt, for this of the Text, <hi>that we have our Judges as at the firſt, and Counſellors as at the beginning;</hi> From which words, to adapt my Diſcourſe to the Time and Perſons preſent, I ſhall conſider.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A Truth imply'd; That the welfare and happineſs of a Nation, and particularly of this, greatly depends upon the having good Judges and wiſe Counſellors.</item>
               <item>2. I ſhall conſider what is meant by <hi>Judges as at the firſt, and Counſellours as at the beginning.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. That the Proſperity of a Nation very much depends upon its having good Judges and good Counſellors. As to the laſt I ſhall not diſcourſe at this time, only this, that ſince the <hi>Wiſe man</hi> tells us, <hi>In the multitude of Counſellors there is ſafty, and where there is no Counſel the People fall,</hi> that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:53338:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>without Counſel Purpoſes are diſappointed, and that no great thing is to be taken in hand but with good advice. 'Tis a happineſs to a People where their Prince maketh choice of, and is advis'd by, wiſe Counſellors, ſince for want thereof things are not ſeldom carried on at a ſtrange rate, and meet with a Fate anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to ſuch raſh and unadviſed Undertakings. And did I think it convenient, I want not matter to enlarge on this Point as to this Nation; but 'tis needleſs, ſince for the want of ſuch Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors, or rather having liv'd under ſuch a one as the <hi>Wiſeman</hi> mentions, <hi>Whoſe way is right in his own Eyes, hath not hearkened unto Counſels,</hi> we are ſufficiently convinc'd of this Truth. And ſo I paſs on to the other Part of the Propoſition, <hi>Judges as at the firſt;</hi> and that <hi>firſt</hi> in general, good Judges do highly promote the Intereſt of a Nation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the Juſtice of Divine Providence; when Juſtice is acted, and Judges act juſtly, when neither Bribery, nor Injuſtice, Oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor perverting of Judgment are in a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, God hath promiſed, yea granted, Security to ſuch a People, and this I might make evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in that all Gods promiſes are conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal, and that as to National Concerns and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53338:4"/>Public Bleſſings, we can have no aſſurance of the enjoyments of Proſperity, but by the living up to the Rules of our Profeſſion, and that 'tis righteouſneſs that exalteth a Nation; That juſtice and righteous Judgment are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded and commended in Scripture, I hope none will deny, and in this Sence our Caſe is like that of the <hi>Jews</hi> in the days of <hi>Samuel, If we ſhall ſtill do wickedly, we ſhall be conſumed both we and our King,</hi> and particularly in the caſe of doing Juſtice and executing juſt Judgment, the Scriptures are plain, ſince this hath ſtop'd and removed Judgments; and the want thereof caus'd God to deal ſeverely with his People: Of many ſuch places, I ſhall beg leave to remind you of ſome few, <hi>Deut.</hi> 16.18. <hi>Judges and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers ſhalt thou make thee, in all thy Gates, and they ſhall Judge the People with juſt Judgment; Thou ſhalt not wreſt Judgment, thou ſhalt not reſpect Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, neither take a Gift, — that which is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther juſt ſhalt thou follow, that thou mayeſt live and inherit the Land which the Lord thy God giveth thee.</hi> No ſecurity of a Nations Proſperity like the due and impartial executing of Judgment and Juſtice; Juſtice which at once adorns and upholds the State, Juſtice that Eſtabliſheth the Throne and exalteth a Nation, Juſtice that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53338:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>Bond and Ligament of Society, which holdeth the Building all together. So that there is no ſurer Symptoms of a decaying State then the want of due Adminiſtration of Juſtice, and when good Judges are turn'd out, we may ſay as <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſaid of <hi>Elijah; Ah the Horſes and Chariots of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>yea as if the Ark it ſelf was gone, the Glory of</hi> Iſrael <hi>is departed,</hi> hence the Prophets term'd ſuch Times evil Times, and ſuch Crimes Crimes of a high and provoking Nature, <hi>Amos</hi> 5.12, 13. <hi>For I know your manifold Tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and your mighty Sins; they afflict the juſt, they take a bribe, and they turn aſide the poor in the gate from their right. Therefore the prudent ſhall keep ſilence in that time, for it is an evil time.</hi> Alas! Alas! What can that Nation expect, where ſuch Judges are? or what can they do to avert thoſe Judgments they feel or fear? or have any hopes of being happy, unleſs they follow the advice before ſubjoined, even hate the evil, and love the good, and eſtabliſh Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Gate: and then it may be that the Lord God of Hoſts will be gracious with the Remnant of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> in vain we boaſt and think our ſelves ſecure as living under a Happy and Eaſy Government, protected by good and wholeſome Laws, and above all, having Gods
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:53338:5"/>true Religion profeſs'd and maintain'd amongſt us, ſince all this ſignifies nothing, unleſs as the Prophet adviſes, <hi>v.</hi> 24. <hi>We let Judgment run down as waters and Righteouſneſs as a mighty ſtream.</hi> The due and impartial Adminiſtration of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice is that which hath removed Judgments, and when <hi>Phineas</hi> executed Judgment, the Plague was ſtayed: this can only ſecure to a Nation the Providence of God, without which our Riches, our Strength, our Wiſdom, our Forces at Sea, or at Land, will ſtand us in no ſtead; if God be on our ſide we need not fear what Man can do againſt us; nor can we take any better courſe to have God on our ſide, than by taking heed to do Juſtice: then, and not till then will God pour out his Bleſſings upon us, <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.5. <hi>If you throughly execute Judgment between a Man and his Neighbour: If ye oppreſs not the Stranger, and the Widdow, and ſhed not innocent Blood in this place, then will I cauſe you to dwell in this place in the Land I gave to your Fathers for ever and ever,</hi> the ſame is repeated, <hi>Cap.</hi> 22. with this promiſe, <hi>v.</hi> 4. <hi>For if ye do this thing indeed; then ſhall there enter in by the Gates, Kings ſitting upon the Throne of</hi> David, <hi>riding in Chariots and on Horſes, he and his Servants, and his People, but if ye will not hear theſe words I ſwear by my ſelf ſaith
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53338:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Lord, that this Houſe ſhall become a Deſolation;</hi> To name no more, this is the laſt Remedy, this is the only way to ſtop or retard an impending Judgment, Jer. 5.1. <hi>Run ye to and fro through the Streets of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and ſee now, and know, and ſeek in the broad places thereof, if ye can find a Man, if there be any that executeth Judgment, that ſeeketh the Truth, and I will pardon it.</hi> And that <hi>de facto,</hi> this is true, is obſervable of all Ages and People. God ever rewarding that Nation with Proſperity, which was careful to obſerve public Juſtice, as was eminent in the Government of the <hi>Romans,</hi> who as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> obſerves were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſed to their keeping Faith and doing Juſtice, and to the <hi>Jews</hi> God himſelf appears, as to the Truth of the Propoſition; <hi>viz.</hi> That the due Execution of Juſtice very much tends to the good and welfare of a People, <hi>Jer.</hi> 22.15. <hi>Did not thy Father eat and drink, and do Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Juſtice, and then it was well with him? He judged the Cauſe of the Poor and Needy, then it was well with him:</hi> So much good, or ſo much evil, do good and evil Judges bring upon a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. 'Tis evident that good Judges do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the Intereſt of a Nation from the End, Office and Authority of Judges. The End and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53338:6"/>Office of a Judg is to preſerve Public Peace, to ſee that no Man ſuffer Injury; that every one en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy his own; they are for the praiſe of them that do well and the puniſhment of them that do ill; now if the Judges be corrupt or negligent in their Places, Virtue will be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, and Vice grow inſolent, and the Manners of Men grow diſſolute and licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, and the whole Nation in a ſhort time be diſorder'd and come to Deſolation. For where the Magiſtrate fails in his Duty, and is corrupt, Great Men will ſoon preſume of Impunity, and mean Ones by their Example will be trampling upon Authority, and then a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions Caſe is like that of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Anarchy, every one will do what is right in his own Eyes. Judges and Magiſtrates, as well as the Supreme Powers, are ordained not for their own ſake, but for the Peoples Safety, that they may have thoſe to whom they may always reſort, and upon whoſe determinations they may depend in all their Difficulties and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, and to this end, and for this very pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, hath God granted the Power and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and for this Cauſe we reverence them, yield them Honour, and pay them Tribute, becauſe they are Gods Miniſters for our good; and are continually attending on this very
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:53338:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſame thing, hence have they thoſe Appellati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Fathers, intimating that all good Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates ſhould have a Fatherly Care over, and bear a Fatherly Affection unto, thoſe, that are under them, they are alſo termed <hi>Shepherds</hi> both in prophane and ſacred Writ, and ought to feed and defend their Flocks, and do that to the State which <hi>David</hi> did to his flock, not ſuffer the Lyon or Bear to take or hurt one poor Lamb amongſt them. Indeed this is a Duty we all owe to our Neighbour, but Judges and Magiſtrates are more eſpecially obliged to uſe the utmoſt of their Power, to let no opportunity ſlip, of helping thoſe to right that ſuffer wrong, to ſtand by their poor Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, who by Great, Rich or Covetous Men are oppreſſed, to protect them from Injuries, and to deliver them out of the hands of ſuch, as are too Mighty, or too Crafty for them, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring by force or fraud, to deprive them of their Lives or Livelihoods, even ſuch good Judges ſhall judge the People according to Right, and defend the Poor, they ſhall keep the ſimple Folk by their right, defend the Children of the poor, and break in pieces the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſor: In a word, the Magiſtrate is placed on high, on purpoſe to take notice of the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53338:7"/>Actions and Demeanors of others, and to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure them; and nothing leſs then a ſincere and conſtant Adminſtration of Juſtice will add weight to their Words, win Awe and Eſteem to their Perſons, preſerve the Authority of their Places, put Life and Activity into their Spirits, and enable them chearfully to do the Work of their Calling, and thereby render the Prince and People Happy, there being (for want of Juſtice) no complaining in the Streets.</p>
            <p>And <hi>3dly,</hi> This is evident from the contrary, nothing tending ſo much to the Ruine of a Nation, as corrupt Judges, who ſoon looſe that Authority and Eſteem which is due to their Places; for can thoſe Magiſtrates Condemn Injuſtice in others, of which they are ſo noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly Guilty themſelves, and when the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy is contemn'd, the Prince by whoſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority they act, is not much valued, and the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is unhinged, ſtands looſe and totter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ready to be diſſolved upon every Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content. You know the Elders of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> thirſty after a Change of Government, but durſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver attempt it till the Sons of <hi>Samuel</hi> by turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſide after Lucre, by taking Bribes, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting Judgment, gave them too fair an Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to move it; and I could eaſily ſhew what
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53338:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>Evils have enſued upon the like occaſions in other Nations; To conclude in general, the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of good Judges are ſuch and ſo many that no Nations can be happy without them. Theſe are they which repreſs all Diſorders, protect the Innocent, keep Peace, uphold the Kings Throne, and turn away Gods Judgments from a Nation, and now what is ſaid of good Judges in general, is eminently true of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in particular, as may appear, from the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of our Government, and the Laws we are to be govern'd by; We of this Nation are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch a happy Conſtitution, that whatever is bad in all Governments is excluded this of ours, and what is good is included in it. For tho we are govern'd by One, yet 'tis by Laws made <hi>Authoritate Parliamenti,</hi> the Legiſlative Power being in the King, Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons. And the Eſſentials of this Government are theſe two, That no Law can be made or repeal'd, or totally diſpens'd with, but by this Power, and That the Kings govern according to the Laws they have made; and therefore as we ſwear Allegiance to the Prince according to Law, ſo the Prince alſo ties himſelf by Oath to govern us by Law; now if the Judges act ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Law, as by Oath they are bound, no
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53338:8"/>Subject can be much injur'd; and in this Senſe, I humbly conceive, is to be underſtood that Maxim in our Common Law, <hi>that the King can do no Wrong;</hi> ſince the Law being his public Will, the Magiſtrate is to act by that, tho the Prince at ſome time ſhould command him to act otherwiſe: I hope I need not prove that the Happineſs of this Nation conſiſts in the Kings juſt Government, and the People's due ſubjection; when there is no Miſunderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings between the Prince and the People, but each concur to make the Commonwealth Happy; now this in a great meaſure depends upon Judges, who not only aſſiſt at the Making and Penning of all Laws, but are to hear and determine Controverſies between the Prince and his Leige People; for tho it be our Duty to preſs home Obedience to lawful Authority, 'tis the Judges who are to tell us, what O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience is due, and they properly, and not Divines, are to determine Points of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; it is not for Divines (ſays the Learned <hi>Sanderſon</hi>) to meddle in theſe Matters, whereof they are not competent Judges, nor do they come within the compaſs of their Sphere, they ought to be left to the cognizance and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of States-men and Lawyers, who
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53338:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>beſt underſtand the Conſtitution of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and the Force and Effect of the Laws of their reſpective Countries, and are therefore preſumed, to be the beſt able to judge the one (by Conſtitution) in whom the Sovereignity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideth, and the other (by Law) how the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereignity is bounded and limited in the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe thereof. 'Tis ſufficiently known the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy of this Nation is limited, and what the Sovereign has, he has by Law; and the ſame Law which grants the King his Legal Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, does alſo as firmly ſecure to the People their juſt Liberties and Properties; and there is none here but knows there are ſundry Caſes, in which the Subject (in maintenance of his right and property) may go to Tryal with the King, bring his Action and have Judgment againſt him in his own Court; and the Judges in ſuch Caſes are bound by their Oaths and Duties to right the Party according to Law, againſt the King, as well as againſt his meaneſt Subject: Now if they are corrupt, and through Fear, or for Preferment, act otherwiſe, we may eaſily conceive what miſchief they may do in the Nation.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:53338:9"/>
            <p n="2">2. The Judges are Judges of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miner</hi> to hear all Cauſes, and to determine ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the known and ſtanding Laws of the Land: So that each Man may have a fair Hearing, and probably a juſt determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Matters. Beſides, the Judges are Overſeers, and may hinder corruption in others. And here I cannot but take occaſion to ſhew, how our Law empowreth the Judges of Aſſize to inſpect all, any ways concern'd, and if they are careful they may regulate, and in a great meaſure prevent thoſe Abuſes, which too often are in the Grand or Petty Jury, in the Accuſer, Witneſs, Pleader, At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney, and inferior Clerks and under-Officers; ſince the Judge is not only bound to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce Sentence according to Law, but 'tis his Duty to ſee that none of his Subjects have Damage. The Kings Majeſty, ſays the Lord <hi>Coke,</hi> at his Coronation, is ſworn to do Juſtice to all his Subjects, which in his own Perſon, it is impoſſible to perform; and therefore his Highneſs is conſtrained by his Miniſters, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties, Juſtices and Judges, to adminiſter Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to his People; unto them, and into their hands is (as it were) deliver'd the Kings own Oath; ſee then the Dignity and Charge of Juſtices.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:53338:9"/>and Judges of Aſſize. <hi>Aſſignavimus vos Juſticia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rios noſtros,</hi> we have aſſigned you our Juſtices, and you may adminiſter Juſtice unto our Subjects, then (ſays he) by the Kings Commiſſion, the Kings Oath is put into our hands; now he that does not forbid an evil, when he may, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands it. Judges then are chiefly entruſted with the Kings Laws, and have a ſuperintendency over all other at the Aſſizes, whoſe duty is to ſee how others do theirs, and to find out what is amiſs in any, and to check and puniſh all as they deſerve, and ſurely when the Judge himſelf is juſt and impartial, the Accuſer, Witneſs, Jurors, Lawyers, and all other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior Officers, if they be not alſo juſt, will yet be afraid and not dare to act unjuſtly bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fac'd and openly, many ſuch things I fear, want a Reformation, and good Judges are the Sanctuary to which every injur'd Perſon flys in diſtreſs. For Princes be they never ſo good, yet cannot know their Subjects wants, they ſee with others Eyes, and hear with others Ears, and are inform'd by others Tongues, and act by others hands; it cannot be ſuppos'd thoſe Conſtellations which attend the Southern Pole ſhould take notice of our Hemiſphere, or intermix their influences with thoſe over our
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:53338:10"/>heads, each Agent muſt act within the Sphere of its activity; then therefore the Reverend Judges, who by the benefit of the Circuit, have advantage of viewing the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and all the Corners thereof, may ſee thoſe Enormities wherewith any Part is infeſted, and are the only Able and Authoriz'd. Perſons to apply their Remedies, and thereby reſtore Church and State, Prince and People, yea the whole Nation to its Priſtine Health and Sound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; upon You chiefly depends the happineſs of this Nation, you who know our Laws, and have Power to put them in Execution; our Laws are made by Authority of Parliament, for the good of the People, but 'tis you that put life into them, which if not duly executed are but dead Letters, ye are the <hi>leges Loquentes,</hi> and by the due and true Execution of our good and wholeſome Laws, you ſhall free this Nation from infinite Miſchiefs, and ſecure to us all that is near and dear to us in this World; and that it is ſo, I might further ſhew from the Evils which have happen'd to this Nation by corrupt Judges; but ſuch Judges as we had lately, the late <hi>Beneplaciti,</hi> have out-done all their Predeceſſors in this Point, and we need only call to mind their unjuſt and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:53338:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>illegal Proceedings, and the Slavery they were bringing upon the Nation, and we muſt needs conclude, that the happineſs of this Nation de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon our having good and upright Judges. The Sum of what I have ſaid is this, that good Judges are the Pillars, that bear up the State and hinder it from Diſſolution; that 'tis in them to make a Nation flouriſh, and a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple glorious, their Righteouſneſs exalting a Nation, and their Sin a great reproach to any People, that by them, and their juſt Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Kings Throne is Eſtabliſhed, and in a Sence made perpetual, that 'tis in their Power to ſtop the Fury of God, and hinder or retard a direful Judgment, you may procure a Bleſſing for a Curſe. More I might add, but I hope the preſent Judges, out of a conſideration of what they owe to God, to their Majeſties, to the whole Nation, and to their own Conſciences, will ſo act, hear and determine all Cauſes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Word of God, and the known and ſtanding Laws of the Land, allowing the King his Legal Prerogatives, and the Subject his juſt Liberty and Property, and in every Caſe pronounce ſuch juſt and righteous Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that it may ſeem needleſs to ſpeak to the Ear, what in our days will be ſo viſible to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53338:11"/>the Eye, we ſeeing our ſelves happy in that we have <hi>Judges at the firſt,</hi> which brings me to them, who I hope are come to us, juſt Judges, <hi>viz.</hi> To ſhew you what is meant by <hi>Judges as at the firſt</hi> and in this I ſhall be brief, and I ſhall <hi>firſt</hi> conſider <hi>Judges as at the firſt,</hi> in general, and <hi>ſecondly</hi> in particular. 1. <hi>Judges as at the firſt</hi> in general, ſuch as God conſtituted at the firſt, and of theſe 'tis requir'd, that they be Men of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Underſtanding, Men that fear God and hate Covetouſneſs, Men of Integrity and Courage, Lovers of Truth, having no reſpect of Perſons, a word or two of each Quality.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Judges at the firſt</hi> were required to be Men of Wiſdom and Underſtanding, <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Take ye Wiſe Men, and Underſtanding, and known among your Tribes, and I will make them Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers over you.</hi> And the charge which is ſubjoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed requires all Judges to be ſuch, even that they may be able rightly to judge between their Brethren, and the Text tells us, the Cauſe which he knew not he ſearched it out; and he then acts as a <hi>Judge as at the firſt,</hi> who when he hath heard both Parties with equal
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:53338:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>Patience, who hath duly examined the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, conſidering who they are, and what they ſay, and well weighed all Evidences and Circumſtances, and trying all other juſt ways of finding out the Truth, then pronounceth Sentence accordingly.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Judges at the firſt</hi> were required to be Men of Integrity and Courage, <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.16. <hi>And I charged your Judges, ſaying, hear the Cauſe between your Brethren, and judge righteouſly between every Man and his Brother, and the Stranger that is with him,</hi> they ſhall not reſpect Perſons in Judgment, but they ſhall hear the ſmall as well as the great, good Judges, and ſuch as were at the firſt, uſed Indifferency in the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of Juſtice, conſidering the Cauſe, abſtract from all Relation but that of Right and Equity, having no reſpect of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons or partial Inelination to any ſide.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Judges at the firſt</hi> were to be Men of Courage, and indeed without this Quality the Law grows weak, and uſeleſs; what fignify good Laws if the Magiſtrate have not Courage enough to put them in Execution, yea for want of this, Magiſtracy becomes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible, and the Oppreſſors grow Inſolent, and like thoſe in the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> cry, <hi>who ſhall ſay
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53338:12"/>unto us, what do ye?</hi> We are Rich, we are Great, and what Judges dare meddle with us, and therefore <hi>Jethro</hi> required this in a Magiſtrate, <hi>viz.</hi> That he ſhould be a Man of Courage, and <hi>Job,</hi> ſpeaking of ſuch a one, tells us, <hi>he broke the Jaws of the Wicked, and pulled the ſpoil out of his Teeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Judges at the firſt</hi> were to be Men that feared God, a Vertue very requiſite in all Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, and therefore the Wicked, the Wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doer, the Oppreſſor, and ſuch as do Violence, are in the Scripture, ſaid, to have no fear of God before their Eyes, and <hi>Abraham</hi> deſpaired of any Juſtice in the Men of <hi>Gerar,</hi> becauſe he thought the Fear of God was not in that Place. <hi>The Fear of God,</hi> ſays <hi>Solomon, is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of Wiſdom,</hi> and 'tis the Fountain of Juſtice, this was urged by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated by good <hi>Jehoſhaphat,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.6. <hi>Take heed what ye do: for ye Judge not for Man, but for the Lord, who is with you in the Judgment. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now, let the fear of the Lord be upon you, take heed and do it: for there is no iniquity in the Lord our God, nor reſpect of Perſons, nor taking of Gifts.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:53338:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Judges at the firſt</hi> were to be Lovers of Truth, they ſhould make it their buſineſs, and count it their Delight to do Juſtice, and not only ſhould they be Lovers of Truth themſelves, but diſcountenance Fraud and Deceit in all others, ſuch as falſe Accuſations, falſe Witneſſes, crafty and cunning Pleaders, by whom a bad Cauſe is made a good one; and in ſome others, we all know, Malice, Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, Ambition, Covetouſneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are apt to give being to many falſe and unjuſt Accuſations, and the Inventors and Teachers of ſuch Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, are cunning, and uſe many Arts and Tricks to give them the colour and face of Truth. Now the Magiſtrate, as a Lover of Truth, ſhould be jealous and uſe his utmoſt skill and induſtry in all ſuſpicious Cauſes, to ſift and bolt out the Truth, and make all ſuch as have a hand in ſuch unjuſt Cauſes, all informing, promoting, pettifogging Raſcals, Examples of his Severity; not in the leaſt encouraging any ſuch make-bates, who are the plague and peſts of the Nation, the brood of <hi>Cain,</hi> who flew his Brother, and Children of the Devil, who is ſtvled the Accuſer of the Nation, who was a Lyar and a Murtherer from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:53338:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly, Judges at the firſt,</hi> were to be Men hating Covetouſneſs, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.8. <hi>Thou ſhalt take no Gift: for the Gift blindeth the Eyes, and perverteth the words of the righteous,</hi> Oh the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous Power of Mony! Oh powerful Guineas, that work upon Men, yea Men of Wiſdom, and Men that are Righteous, ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping their Ears, blinding their Eyes, and hiding their Heads, that they neither hear, nor ſee, nor act juſtly in a Cauſe; and thoſe Judges who will receive Bribes, or may be dealt with or ſpoken to in their Chambers, do not reſpect the Cauſe of the ſaid innocent Perſon, nor the Law but Gifts; I might in this be large, but enough if not too much, becauſe I ſpeak to thoſe, who, I hope, deteſt and abhor all ſuch vile Practices, and may we be ſo happy as to have no corrupt Officers, no pact Jury, or any other who will receive a reward to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert Judgment, and get the day of their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary, when his Cauſe is more righteous then theirs, thus much I have ventured to ſay of Judges <hi>as at the firſt,</hi> in general; a word or two of <hi>Judges as at the firſt,</hi> in reference, to this Nation in particular.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:53338:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="1">1. Then <hi>Judges as at the firſt</hi> muſt be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Conſtituted, being Commiſſion'd by the Sovereign Power, and their Commiſſion extends to hear and determine all Cauſes between Party and Party, and alſo between the King and the Party depending, to Acquit or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn all ſuch Priſoners, as for any Offences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Majeſty's Crown and Dignity ſhall be brought before them: So that their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion is large and abſolute, they having Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority by Vertue of their Commiſſion, as in the Perſon of our Sovereign, to judge in Cauſes that do concern the Life and Death of the Subject. And all this that Juſtice may by them receive a full, ſound and perfect Execution. Now note they are to act as their Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſaith the Lord <hi>Coke,</hi> doth appoint, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit and command: We then, ſays he, the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of Aſſize and Goal Delivery, are by his Majeſty appointed to Adminiſter Juſtice unto his Subjects, but <hi>quo modo,</hi> not according to our Will, Conceit or Opinion, but <hi>Secundum Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem &amp; Conſuetudinem Maneriae Anglicanae,</hi> which Law, Cuſtom and Manner muſt be Executed with Judgment, Underſtanding and Equity; for we muſt know our ſelves, and the place wherein we are, we muſt know and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:53338:14"/>each Cauſe before us brought, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our Knowledge and Underſtanding we muſt uprightly judge according to Equity, without, in the leaſt ſort, being drawn by reſpecting either Perſon, or Quality, to bear a partial Hand in the Execution of Judgment. Briefly, ſays he, the Office of a Judge is to hear each Party ſpeak ſolemnly, to anſwer or object directly, to ſee (as near as may be poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) each Truth ſubſtantially proved, and then to Judge with an upright Heart, according to Juſtice and Equity, never in any one thing making a concluſion before a conſcionable, wiſe and judicial conſideration. As to the Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes they are to enquire of, they are, ſays he, ſuch as theſe by whom the King is moſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obeyed, his Eſtate diſturbed, and Kingdoms threatned, and that the Peace be inviolably kept, of which and much more you may ſee in the Chapter of <hi>Judges,</hi> and amongſt the reſt, that they take care of Religion, and therefore <hi>Judges as at the firſt,</hi> as I could inſtance in ſeveral Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, were wont to let thoſe who heard them, know, that they ought to be very careful in ſuch Matters. And here of a plain Inſtructor I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a humble Petitioner to the Reverend Judges, to the Worſhipful the Juſtice, to the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:53338:14"/>Gentlemen of the Grand Inqueſt, and all in Places of Eminency, in the behalf of the Eſtabliſh'd Religion of the Land, againſt her many, and ſometimes too powerful Enemies; I hope, I need not, to you at leaſt, make mention of thoſe Maxims, of our Common-Law, that <hi>nunquam proſpere ſuccedunt humana, ubi negliguntur divina,</hi> that <hi>ſumma eſt ratio quae pro religione facit,</hi> that <hi>gravius eſt divinam quam temporalem laedere Majeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem,</hi> that Religion and Juſtice are the main Pillars of the Common-wealth, and that the Frame of our <hi>Magna Charta</hi> is, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſhall be free, and ſhall have all her whole Rights and Liberties inviolable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> That his preſent Majeſty hath ſworn to maintain the Church <hi>England,</hi> as it is by Law Eſtabliſhed, now I beſeech you according to theſe Maxims, and as you are intruſted with the Kings Oath, and are bound to act accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Law, maintain the Church by Law Eſtabliſhed, againſt all her Adverſaries whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, and chiefly I intreat you, againſt Atheiſts, Haters of Epiſcopacy, and Contemners of our publick Liturgy. <hi>Firſt,</hi> lend your helping hand againſt all thoſe Athieſts, who make a mock at Religion, and all that is Sacred, or but Serious amongſt us; neither you, nor we, can
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:53338:15"/>make Men truly Pious, or baniſh Impiety out of the Nation; but you may, yea ought to be, careful of Religion; as that which is the beſt Security to the Nation, ſince neither Forts nor Caſtles, Armies nor Navies, Arms nor Amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, Men nor Money, to ſay nothing of Allies and Confederates, the Staff of <hi>Egypt,</hi> are not ſo powerful to ſupport the Crown of a Prince as Religion. You are here in the Kings Name, and act by his Commiſſion; let me intreat you then to act under him as Defenders of the Holy Ancient and moſt Catholick Faith, taught and profeſt in this Church of <hi>England;</hi> ſuffer not this holy Religion to be deſpiſed, let not this be openly derided, droll'd upon, ridicul'd or turn'd into Burleſque and Mockery, as if our Young Squire and Witty Spark, had no way to ſhew his Wit and Breeding then by expoſing the Clergy, and making a Ridicule of Religion, who indeed (how witty ſoever he thinks himſelf) is a greater Fool, then he in the <hi>Pſalmiſt, ſaying in the Street, what he only did in his Heart, there is no God.</hi> As to the <hi>ſecond,</hi> thoſe who are ſworn Enemies to Epiſcopacy, and never had good Will for Biſhops unleſs when in their Power; I know you cannot perſwade them to lay aſide thoſe ill and unjuſt Principles they
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:53338:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>have unwarily imbibed from ſome Teachers, much leſs perſwade them to admit of this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment as Apoſtolical; but I hope, you will not ſuffer any bitter Spirit, in Pulpit, or Preſs, to burſt forth into Scandalous and Slanderous Libels, bitter Paſquels and railing Pamphlets, whereby they Slander that Sacred Government, which (by the joynt Confeſſion of all Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Divines) and by the moſt irrefragable Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of our own, is proved to derive it ſelf from the Times of the Bleſſed Apoſtles, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any interruption or alteration; for tho the Bounty of Religious Princes have thought meet to grace the Function with ſome Acceſſes of Tithes and Maintenance, as yet they are by Law in this Nation, who that is Wiſe, or who indeed, but a Fool, will thence argue, that the ſubſtance or any eſſential Part thereof is in the leaſt part altered by ſuch gracious Munificence? And that I may not ſeem to digreſs, know E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy is ſetled by Law, and the Lord <hi>Coke</hi> long ago obſerved, that the Oppoſers of Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy ſtrove to ſhake in ſunder the whole Frame of this Imperial Government; for if (as they deſire) ſays he, the Form of our Civil Law was Abrogated, then ſhould our Common Law, and it of neceſſity, fall together; for
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:53338:16"/>they are ſo Woven and Incorporated together, as that without the one, the other cannot ſtand, and of this he gives the trueſt inſtance, again, ſays he, without the Grave Aſſembly of the Reverend Biſhops, his Majeſties High Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould be unfurniſh'd, no Law being there enacted, but that which is by the King, his Lords Spiritual and Temporal, concluding that thoſe that would have no Biſhops amongſt us, do, in their deſigns, ſtrive to pluck from his Majeſty and the Dignity of his State, the Right Hand of Government, and as much as in them lies, break in ſunder the Golden Frame of juſt Authority; for if no Biſhops, no Laws; if no Laws, no King.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> As to her Enemies who contemn and deride our Litany, that Public Form of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, uſed in our Churches, tho you cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade Men to Worſhip God in Unity and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, as was commanded in the days of Queen of <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of Bleſſed Memory, yet ſuffer not the Public and Eſtabliſhed Worſhip of the Nation, to be deprived of its due Honour and Eſteem, as that which being ſelected out of Scripture, and the Antient Models of holy Church, and continued by the holy Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, our bleſſed Reformers, and hath received
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:53338:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>abundant Supplies of Strength from the zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Commendations of all our Proteſtant Princes, and the Eſtabliſhment of many Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as that which was the happy means of bringing many out of Popery, and does, in a great meaſure, prevent that Confuſion, Tauto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, Irreverence, not to ſay Blaſphemy, too frequent in extemporary Prayer; in a word, tho you cannot perſwade all Men to frequent the Church of <hi>England</hi>'s Religious Service, and to live in Communion with it; yet aſſure your ſelves ye ſhall do eminent Service to God, to their Majeſtys, to the whole Nation, and in a great meaſure contribute to her Peace and Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, if ye in your ſeveral Stations, by your Grave Speeches and Pious Example ſhall in public, and when occaſion is offered, make it your buſineſs earneſtly to recommend the Wellfare, Order and Conſtitution of this Church, as that which is agreeable to the Scripture, and the Practices of the pureſt Ages in the Chriſtian Church, as that which has been look'd upon, and has proved the main Bulwark of the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt Popery in all Ages; and therefore is that, againſt which <hi>Rome</hi> hath ever ſo bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inveigh'd, and by Power and Fraud labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to overthrow, as that which beſt ſuits with
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:53338:17"/>the Civil Government, neither encroaching upon the Kings Prerogative, nor the Peoples Liberty, as happens both from the Popes Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy and the Kirks Independency, no Cannon can be made in <hi>England,</hi> but by the Conſent and Authority of the King, nor any ſo made is of force, if contrary to the Laws of the Land, as that Conſtitution which is moſt agreeable to the Genius of the Nation, and Temper of <hi>Engliſhmen;</hi> there being no other ſort of Church Government, ſo well pleaſing to the generality of the People, as this; for whatever Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (of all the contending Parties of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) ſhould chance to get uppermoſt, it would have more Enemies then this has; and ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we would have none, and nothing but Confuſion, we ought in Point of Prudence to ſtick to this; for tho it hath had, and Oh! ſtill hath, many and great Oppoſers, yet hath it kept its ground; nor could all the Force and Fraud of <hi>Rome</hi> quite overpower her: For this Church, which regularly ſhoke off the <hi>Roman</hi> Yoak, watering the infant Plant with he Blood, hath for above a hundred Year been upheld by the unwearied Pains and great Learning of the <hi>Prelatic</hi> Party, nor can the World ſhew ſuch ſtrength of Argument and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:53338:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>Solid Confutation of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>'s Works as in the Writings of the Church of <hi>England</hi> Men; again, that 'tis a Conſtitution capable of preſerving it ſelf, not pragmatical, like the Conclave or Conſiſtory, to Arraign Kings and States, and make the Aſſembly or Conclave above the Parliament: Yet her Superiors have by Law an undoubted Right to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at thoſe Debates, and the making thoſe Laws which concern the good of the People, and ſo in a great meaſure able to provide a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any that attempt her Ruin; again, as that Conſtitution which is not only good at home, but prais'd and admired by all Foreign Churches abroad; as the Honour as well as Defence of the whole Reformation: And <hi>Laſtly,</hi> as that which hath ſecured to us our Laws, Liberties and Lives, theſe being the Men, who dared to oppoſe (tho mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly) the Diſpenſing Power, and would not yield with the Trimmer, nor be wheadled with the Diſſenter, to ſet up Popery and Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Power; and therefore I hope every good Magiſtrate and conſiderate <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> (tho they bear with the Infirmities of the weak where ſuch are) will yet have an Eye to all
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:53338:18"/>thoſe who have any ill will at <hi>Sion,</hi> and ſuch as watch to break down all our Carved Work with Axes and Hammers, that labour with might and main, to render the Church of <hi>England</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious in the Eye of the People, and with both hands caſt Fire into the Sanctuary, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring by ill and untoward Speeches to alienate the Hearts and Affections of the People from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and to raiſe Scandals upon all that at this day ſhall ſpeak or write in Her juſt Defence, loading the Conformable Clergy with Contempt, and, as far as they dare, expoſing them in all Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, as well knowing if they can but eject the <hi>Shepherd,</hi> or dreſs him up in a Wolves Skin, the task is not great, the whole Flock being then an eaſiy Prey; but I hope we have <hi>Judges as at the firſt,</hi> and the <hi>King will have Counſellors as at the beginning,</hi> then who will ſay that we want any ordinary and legal Security to make us Happy; Oh! may all our Magiſtrates prove ſuch, and may we all act and live as they direct us. Then may this Nation again take root down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and bear fruit upwards, then may <hi>Ireland</hi> be reduc'd, and the <hi>Monſieur</hi> tremble, and we be happy at home, and feared abroad.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:53338:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>Oh! may we thus live under the Protection of a Wiſe and Juſt Government, eating the Fruit of our Labour! Oh! well are we, and happy ſhall we be; yea, happy are the People that are in ſuch a Caſe; To that end, and for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of theſe his Mercies, let us in the words of our Church (in the Homily for Obedience) heartily thank God for his great and excellent Benefit and Providence concerning Kings, let us pray for them, that they may have Gods Favour and Protection, that they may ever in all things have God to be their Guide, let us pray, that they may have Wiſdom, Juſtice, Strength, Clemency and Zeal to Gods Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the Good of Chriſtian Souls, and the Commonwealth; let us pray they may rightly uſe their Sword and Authority for the Maintenance and Defence of the Catholic Faith, and of their good and honeſt Subjects; and let us pray for our ſelves, that we may be godly in Holy and Chriſtian Converſation, and ſo ſhall we have God on our ſide; and then let us not fear what Man can do unto us; ſo ſhall we live in Obedience both to our moſt Merciful King in Heaven, and to our moſt Chriſtian King on Earth; ſo ſhall we pleaſe God, have
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:53338:19"/>Peace of Conſclence, Reſt and Quiet here, and Eternal Bliſs hereafter, Which he grant us all, who was delivered to death for us, and is now ſet down at the Right hand of God in Heaven.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
